Welcome back, In this video, we're going to continue our lecture on lexical
欢迎回来，在这段视频中，我们将继续我们关于词汇的讲座
analysis with some examples from past programming languages where interesting
用一些过去编程语言中有趣的例子进行分析
lexical problems arose. So we've already talked a little bit about Fortran and what
词汇问题出现了。我们已经讨论了一些关于Fortran的内容
are the interesting lexical rules in Fortran is the white space is
Fortran中有趣的词汇规则是空格是
insignificant so white space doesn't matter and something like VAR1 to which
无关紧要，所以空格无关紧要，像VAR1这样的东西
could be a variable name VAR1 is exactly the same as VA R1 so these two program
可能是变量名VAR1与VA R1完全相同，所以这两个程序
fragments have to mean exactly the same thing sand the idea in Fortran is that you
片段的含义必须完全相同，Fortran中的概念是
can take your program and you could delete all the blanks from it and that shouldn't
可以拿走你的程序，你可以删除其中的所有空白，但这不应该
change what the program means at all. Let's take a look at an example of how
完全改变程序的含义。让我们来看一个例子，看看如何
Fortran's white space rule affects lexical analysis. Here are a couple of Fortran
Fortran的空格规则会影响词法分析。这里有几个Fortran
code fragments and I should say that this example is taken from the dragon book and
代码片段，我应该说这个例子取自“龙之书”，
actually couple of the later examples were also taken from an older edition of the
实际上，后面的几个示例也取自旧版本的
dragon book. But anyway what we have here, this is actually the header of a Fortran
龙书。但不管怎么说，这实际上是一个Fortran的标题
loop. And you know it's a loop because it has the key word do, which is like four in
循环。你知道这是一个循环，因为它有一个关键字do，就像4英寸
modern C or C++ so I'd say loop key word And then we have out iteration variable I
现代的C或C++，所以我会说循环关键字，然后我们就有了输出迭代变量i
and we have a range that I will vary between. So, in this case I will go from
我们有一个范围，我会在这个范围内变化。所以，在这种情况下，我将从
one up to 25. And then this number five here, this is a little bit odd, something
一张最多25张。然后这里的第五个数字，这有点奇怪，
you don't see in modern languages. In the old days in Fortran you would have your do
你在现代语言中是看不到的。在过去的Fortran中，你可以随心所欲
statement at the top of the loop and then the size of the loop or all the statements
语句，然后是循环的大小或所有语句
included in the loop Were named by a label, they came right after the do
包括在循环中的是由标签命名的，它们紧跟在DO之后
statement. So, the loop will extend from the, the header, the do statement down to
声明。因此，循环将从、头、do语句向下扩展到
the label five. So whatever statement was able with five, all of the statements in
五号标签。所以无论什么语句都可以有5个，所有的语句都在
between would be part of the loop. And so, the loop would execute those statements
会是循环的一部分。因此，循环将执行这些语句
then we'll go back around to the header and then we keep executing those until it
然后，我们将返回到头文件，然后继续执行这些文件，直到它
had done so for every one of the values of the iteration variable, in this case, one
已经为迭代变量的每个值执行了此操作，在本例中为一个
to 25. Now, here's a nother code fragment and as you can see this one is almost
到25岁。现在，这是另一个代码片段，如您所见，这个代码片段几乎
exactly the same as the one above. The only difference is, let me just switch
和上面的一模一样。唯一的区别是，让我换一下
colors, is here that this particular fragment has a comma in that position and
颜色，在这里这个特定的片段在那个位置有一个逗号，
this fragment has a period. And it turns out that this difference makes all the
此片段有句点。事实证明，这种不同使得所有的
difference that these two fragment of code mean completely different things. So, this
区别在于这两段代码的含义完全不同。那么这个呢，这个
fragment, the first one, is in fact a do loop as I said before so it has the
正如我前面所说，第一个片段实际上是一个DO循环，所以它有
keyword do, the label five, the variable I and the range one to 25. Now this fragment
关键字DO、标签5、变量I和范围1到25。现在这个片段
down here, this is actually a variable name, do 5I, So far as writing without the
在这里，这实际上是一个变量名，do 5i，只要不使用
blanks. Remember the blanks don't matter, This would be do 5I and this is an
一片空白。记住，空格并不重要，这将是Do 5i，这是一个
assignment equals the number 1.25. Okay, And so you can see here these symbols, the
赋值等于数字1.25。好的，所以你可以在这里看到这些符号，
sequence, the first sequence of symbols is interpreted completely differently
序列，则对第一个符号序列的解释完全不同
depending on whether there's a period or a comma further on. And so let's just be a
取决于后面是句号还是逗号。所以让我们只做一个
little more precise about that. How do we know what do is? So let's just focus on
关于这一点稍微精确一点。我们怎么知道什么是Do？所以让我们把注意力集中在
the keyword here do and when we're at this point, when our focus is here right after
这里的关键字做，当我们在这一点上，当我们的焦点在这里之后
the zero. And keep in mind that, that the way this is going to be implemented is by
零。请记住，实现这一点的方式是通过
a left to right scan so we're going to be walking in this direction over the, over
一次从左到右的扫描，所以我们将朝这个方向走，完毕
the input looking at each character successfully and when our focus reaches
成功查看每个字符的输入，当我们的焦点到达
this point, we can make a decision. Is this a, is this a keyword 'cause we've
在这一点上，我们可以做出决定。这是，这是个关键词吗，因为我们
seen the entire keyword too. And the problem is that we don't have information
我也看到了整个关键字。问题是我们没有信息
to make that decision. We don't know whether this is do or whether it's going
才能做出这个决定。我们不知道这是真的还是会
to be eventually be part of a variable name like do 5I. And the only way to know
最终成为像do 5i这样的变量名的一部分。唯一能知道的方法就是
is to look ahead in the input to this position to see whether there's a comma or
就是向前看这个位置的输入，看看有没有逗号或
a period there. So this is an example of lexical analysis that requires look ahead.
在那里有一段时间。这是一个词汇分析的例子，需要向前看。
In order to understand the role of due, as we're going left to right. We have to pick
为了理解DUE的作用，我们从左到右。我们得选一个
ahead of the input to see some symbols that come later on. And we can't possibly
在输入之前查看稍后出现的一些符号。我们不可能
disambiguate role of do until that poin t because up to this point, the sequence and
消除DO在位置测试之前作用歧义，因为到目前为止，序列和
the symbols are exactly the same and so the only thing that distinguishes them is
这些符号是完全相同的，所以唯一区别它们的是
something that's much, much further on. And as you can imagine, having lots of
一些更遥远、更遥远的事情。正如你可以想象的，有很多
look ahead complicates the implementation of lexical analysis and so one of the
展望未来会使词法分析的实现复杂化，因此
goals in the design of lexical systems is to minimize the amount of the look ahead
词汇系统设计的目标是将前瞻的数量降到最低。
or bound the amount of look ahead that is required. So you might wonder why Fortran
或限定所需的前瞻时间。所以你可能会想为什么Fortran
has this funny rule about white space. It turns out that on punch card machines it
有一条关于空格的有趣规则。原来，在穿孔卡片机上，
was easy to add extra blanks by accidents and as a result they added this rule to
很容易意外地添加额外的空格，因此他们将此规则添加到
the language so the punch card operator wouldn't have to redo their work all the
语言，这样穿孔卡操作员就不需要从头到尾重做他们的工作
time. Fortunately today we don't enter our programs anymore on punch cards. But this
时间到了。幸运的是，今天我们不再通过打孔卡进入我们的计划。但是这件事
example does help us understand better what we're trying to do in lexical
示例确实帮助我们更好地理解了我们试图在词法中做什么
analysis so as I said the goal is to partition the string. We're trying to buy
分析，正如我所说，目标是对字符串进行分区。我们要买的是
the string up into the logically units of the language. And this is implemented by
将字符串放入语言的逻辑单元中。这是通过以下方式实现的
reading left to right. So we're doing a left to right scan over the input,
从左到右阅读。所以我们要对输入进行从左到右的扫描，
recognizing one token at a time. And because of that, look ahead may be
一次识别一个令牌。正因为如此，向前看可能会是
required to decide where one token ends and the next token begins. And again, I
需要决定一个令牌在哪里结束，下一个令牌在哪里开始。再说一遍，我
want to stress that look ahead is always needed but we would like to minimize the
我想强调的是，向前看总是需要的，但我们想尽量减少
amount of look ahead. And in fact, we like to bound it to some constant to this,
向前看的量。事实上，我们喜欢把它限制在某个常数上，
because it will simplify the implementation of lexical analyzer quite a
因为它将大大简化词法分析器的实现
bit. Now just to illustrate to look ahead is something that we always have to worry
有点。现在，仅仅是为了说明一下，展望未来，这是我们总是要担心的事情。
about. Let's consider this example which we've looked at before and just notice
关于。让我们考虑一下我们之前看过的这个例子，请注意
that when we're reading left to right, let's look at this keyword else here, when
当我们从左到右阅读时，让我们看看这里的其他关键字，当
we read the E. We have to decide is that a variable name or some symbol but itself or
我们读的是E。我们必须决定是变量名还是某个符号，而不是它本身，或者
do we want to consider it together with the symbols that follow them. And so
我们是否要将其与后面的符号一起考虑。因此，
there's a look ahead issue here. After we scanned E, we have to decide does that sit
这里有一个前瞻性的问题。在我们扫描了E之后，我们必须决定这个位置
by itself or is it part of a larger lexical unit? And, you know there a re
它本身还是一个更大的词汇单位的一部分？而且，你知道有一个Re
single character variable names in this example like I, J, and Z and so it's not
本例中的单字符变量名如I、J和Z，因此不是
unreasonable that E could also be one and another example is this double-equals.
不合理的是，E也可以是1，而另一个例子就是这个双等式。
When we read a single equal sign, how do we decide whether that's a single equals
当我们读到一个等号时，我们如何判断这是不是一个等号呢
like these other assignments or that it's really a double-equals. Well, in order to
就像这些其他任务一样，或者这真的是一个双等分。那么为了
do that, if our focus point is right here, we have to look ahead and see. There's
做到这一点，如果我们的焦点就在这里，我们必须向前看，看看。那里有
another = coming up and that's how we know or how we will know. That we wanted to
另一个=即将到来，这就是我们如何知道或我们将如何知道。我们想要
combine it into a single symbol instead of considering this equals by itself. Another
将其合并为单个符号，而不是将其单独视为相等。另一个
example from a, a language from long ago PL [inaudible] is a interesting language.
很久以前的一种语言PL[听不见]是一种有趣的语言。
It was designed by IBM and it stands for Programming Language One. Alright, It was
它是由IBM设计的，它代表编程语言One。好吧，是这样的
designed to be the programming language. At least with an IBM that would be used by
被设计成编程语言。至少与IBM一起使用，该IBM将由
everybody and is supposed to encompass all the features that every programmer would
每个人都可以使用，并且应该包含每个程序员都会使用的所有功能
ever need. And as such, it was supposed to be very, very general and have very few
从来不需要。因此，它被认为是非常，非常普遍的，只有很少的
restrictions. And so, one of the features of PL [inaudible] is that Keywords are not
限制。因此，PL[听不见]的特征之一是关键字不是
reserved. So, in PL [inaudible] you can use a keyword both as a keyword and also
保留的。因此，在PL[Indible]中，您既可以将关键字用作关键字，也可以将其用作关键字
as a variable. So you can use keywords and other roles other than keywords and that
作为一个变量。因此您可以使用关键字和其他角色，而不是关键字
means you can write interesting, interesting sentences or interesting
意思是你可以写有趣的句子或者有趣的句子
programs like this. And let me just read this out loud because it sounds
像这样的节目。让我把这个大声读出来，因为它听起来
interesting, if else then, then = else, else = then. And the correct organization
有趣的是，如果不是这样，那么=Else，Else=Then。和正确的组织
here of course is that this is a keyword, this is a keyword and this is a keyword.
这里当然是这是一个关键字，这是一个关键字，这是一个关键字。
And the other things, switch colors here, are all variables. These are all variable
其他的东西，这里切换颜色，都是变量。这些都是可变的
names. And as you can imagine this mix a lexical analysis somewhat difficult
名字。正如你可以想象的那样，这种混搭的词汇分析有些困难
because when we're just scanning left to right like when we're coming through here
因为当我们从左向右扫描的时候，就像我们经过这里的时候
when we say we're at to this point, you know how do we decide whether these things
当我们说我们已经到了这一步，你知道我们是如何决定这些事情是否
are going to be variable names or keywords without seeing what's going on in the rest
将是变量名或关键字，而不会看到睡觉中发生了什么
of the expression so lexical analysis in PL [inaudible] was quite challenging. So
因此，在PL[听不见]中进行词法分析是相当有挑战性的。所以
here's another example from PL [inaudible]. Here we have a program
这里有另一个来自PL[听不见]的例子。这里我们有一个节目
fragment, we have the word declare and then an open paren and a close paren
片段，我们有单词Declare，然后是一个开放的Paren和一个关闭的Paren
encompassing a bunch of arguments so we'll point out the balance parens here and then
包含了一堆参数，所以我们会在这里指出平衡的花括号
just a list of n things inside the parens. And it turns out that the pending on the
只有一张家长内n件东西的清单。结果是待决的
larger context in which this whole expressions sits, this could be either a
整个表达式所处的更大的上下文中，这可以是一个
keyword. Or it could be in array reference that mean when, yeah, that mean declare
关键字。或者它可以在数组引用中，这意味着，是的，这意味着声明
here could either be a keyword or it could be a name of an array and this could be
这里可以是关键字，也可以是数组的名称，这可以是
the end [inaudible] to the array. And as it happens, there is no way looking at
阵列的末端[听不见]。碰巧的是，我们不可能看到
just this much that we can decide. This fragment is valid, is a valid declaration
就这么多，我们可以决定。此片段有效，是有效的声明
and it's also a valid array reference. So, it would depend on what came next. It
它也是一个有效的数组引用。因此，这将取决于接下来会发生什么。它
might depend on for example whether there was an equal sign here in which cases
可能取决于，例如这里是否有等号，在哪些情况下
would be interpreted as an assignment and, and declare would be the name of an array.
将被解释为赋值，而DECLARE将是数组的名称。
And, the interesting thing about this example is that because the number of
这个例子的有趣之处在于，因为
arguments in here is unbounded. There could be n of them for any n. This
这里的参数是无界的。任何n个都可能有n个。这个
requires unbounded look ahead. Okay, So to implement this properly as you're scanning
需要无拘无束地向前看。好的，为了在你扫描的时候正确地实现这一点
left to right to decide whether declare again is a keyword or re-reference, we
从左到右确定DECLARE AUDE是关键字还是重新引用，我们
would have to scan beyond this entire argument list to see what came next.
必须在整个参数列表之外进行扫描，看看接下来会发生什么。
Fortren and PL [inaudible] were designed in the 1950s and 1960s respectively and
Fortren和PL[无声]分别设计于20世纪50年代和60年代，
those experiences taught us a lot about what not to do in the lexical design of
这些经历教会了我们很多关于在词汇设计中不应该做的事情
programming languages. So things are a lot better today but the problems have not
编程语言。所以今天的情况好多了，但问题并没有
gone away completely and I'll use an example from C++ that illustrate this. So
完全消失了，我将使用C++中的一个示例来说明这一点。所以
here's an example of C++ template syntax which you may be familiar with or you may
下面是C++模板语法的一个示例，您可能很熟悉，也可能
have seen the similar syntax in Java. And C++ has another operator called Stream
我在Java中看到过类似的语法。C++有另一个运算符，称为Stream
Input. So this operator here reads from an input stream and stores the results in a
输入。所以这里的运算符从输入流中读取并将结果存储在
variable. And the problem is, here that there's a conflict with nested templates,
变量。问题是，这里与嵌套模板存在冲突，
So for example, if I have a template o peration that looks like this. Okay.
例如，如果我有一个类似这样的模板操作。好吧。
Notice what happens here. So my intention here is to have a nested application of
注意这里发生了什么。所以我在这里的目的是让嵌套的应用程序
templates but I wind up with two great than signs together at the end and this
模板，但我在最后得到了两个比符号更好的符号，这是
looks just like the stream operator and the question is what should the lexical
看起来就像流运算符，问题是词法应该是什么
analyzer do? Should it interpret this as two close brackets for template or should
分析器做什么？它应该将此解释为模板的两个右括号，还是应该
it interpret it as a two greater than signs stuck together as a stream operator.
它将其解释为2大于作为流运算符粘在一起符号。
And it turns out that for a very long time, I think most C++ compilers have now
事实证明，在很长一段时间里，我认为大多数C++编译器现在都有
fixed this. The C++ compiler in this situation would regard this as a stream
已修复此问题。在这种情况下，C++编译器会将其视为流
operator and you would get a syntax there. And what do you think the solution was, it
运算符，您将在那里获得语法。你认为解决方案是什么，它
turns out that the only fix that you could really do to make this lexically analyzed
事实证明，您真正能做的唯一修复方法是对此进行词法分析
the correct way was to insert a blank so you would have to write this and you would
正确的方法是插入一个空格，这样您就必须这样写，这样您就可以
have to remember to put the blank in there so that the two greater than signs were
必须记得把空格放在那里，这样两个比符号大的
not together. And you know that's kind of ugly that we have to put in white space to
不是在一起。你知道，这是一种丑陋，我们必须放在空白处
fix the lexical analysis of the program. So to summarize the goal of lexical
修正程序的词法分析。综上所述，词汇学的目标是
analysis is to partition the input streams into lexemes, okay. So we have drop down
分析就是将输入流划分成词位，好的。所以我们有下拉菜单
dividing lines in the string to decide where the lexemes lie and we want to
在字符串中分隔线以确定词位所在的位置，我们希望
identify the token of each lexeme, And because, exactly because we're doing a
确定每个词位的标记，因为，正是因为我们在做一个
left to right scan, sometimes we have to have look ahead. Sometimes we have to peek
从左向右扫描，有时我们必须向前看。有时我们不得不偷看
ahead in the input string to figure out what the current string we're looking at,
在输入字符串的前面，以确定我们正在查看的当前字符串是什么，
what the current substring we're looking at, what role it plays in the language?
我们当前看到的子字符串是什么，它在语言中扮演什么角色？